<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom"><title>porfirio's blog - fc29</title><link href="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/" rel="alternate"></link><link href="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/feeds/fc29.atom.xml" rel="self"></link><id>https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/</id><updated>2018-11-29T02:53:00-06:00</updated><entry><title>i3</title><link href="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/posts/2018/11/29/i3.html" rel="alternate"></link><published>2018-11-29T02:53:00-06:00</published><updated>2018-11-29T02:53:00-06:00</updated><author><name>Porfirio Páiz</name></author><id>tag:porfiriopaiz.github.io,2018-11-29:/site/posts/2018/11/29/i3.html</id><summary type="html">&lt;p class="first last"&gt;Improved tiling wm&lt;/p&gt;
</summary><content type="html">&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how to do a Fedora 29 installation with the i3
window manager. It is common to see installation guides for i3, but they assume
that you already have another desktop environment previously installed.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post we will see how to build a fully functional environment from a
minimal installation as I have explained in other publications.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="creating-an-installation-medium"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating an installation medium&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="download-the-iso-fedora-everything-netinstall"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Download the ISO Fedora Everything Netinstall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;From the site: &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://alt.fedoraproject.org/"&gt;https://alt.fedoraproject.org/&lt;/a&gt; download the file of the All
section, this is an ISO that works as a means of installation by network that
downloads all the packages that will be part of the system from the Internet,
as well as gives the option to choose which package collections to install,
unlike Lives media whose software selection has been previously defined.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Download the ISO with wget:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;wget -N -t 0 -c https://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/fedora/linux/releases/29/Everything/x86_64/iso/Fedora-Everything-netinst-x86_64-29-1.2.iso&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also download the integrity check file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;wget -N -t 0 -c https://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/fedora/linux/releases/29/Everything/x86_64/iso/Fedora-Everything-29-1.2-x86_64-CHECKSUM&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Check the integrity of the file:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;sha256sum -c Fedora-Everything-29-1.2-x86_64-CHECKSUM&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="create-the-installation-media-with-fedora-media-writer"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Create the installation media with Fedora Media Writer&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fedora Media Writer is available for different operating systems, download the
corresponding one.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;It is very important to create the installation medium with Fedora Media Writer
since this tool guarantees that the installation medium will have support to
boot on computers that have both UEFI or BIOS.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;How it will start will depend on which of the two has the highest priority
during startup. I always use UEFI only, so all my systems are installed in UEFI
mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://github.com/FedoraQt/MediaWriter/releases/tag/4.1.1"&gt;https://github.com/FedoraQt/MediaWriter/releases/tag/4.1.1&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;When Fedora Media Writer is installed on our computer, we connect our USB
memory, run Fedora Media Writer and use the Custom Image option to navigate to
the path where the ISO is, the one we just downloaded, select it, select
carefully the USB memory we will use and record the image in the USB memory.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installation"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installation&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I have followed the installation steps described in this previous post, making
sure I have access to a wireless network or a wired network.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/blog/posts/anaconda-y-lvm-sobre-luks.html"&gt;https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/blog/posts/anaconda-y-lvm-sobre-luks.html&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This time I had to use my mobile phone, although it is true I had access to a
wireless network during the installation of the base system (Fedora Custom
Install), after installation the packages collection of does not provide the
network drivers required to access wireless networks since they are not
included in the Custom Install selection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;That's why I created a wired network via USB with my mobile phone. To make it
work you have to make sure of the following right after the first boot once the
installation finishes:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Log in in the system.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the USB cable to the computer.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Connect the other end to the mobile phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the phone is connected to a wireless network or that the data plan
is activated. As a note, consider that you need at least 800MB of data in
RPM packages that must be downloaded for a minimum installation of Fedora
with support for the graphical environment with i3wm.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Make sure the phone is in USB or MTP data transfer mode.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Activate a wired network or Tethered Wired Network from your mobile phone.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After this, you should have access to the Internet. Check it by pinging Google:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;ping 8.8.8.8&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="basic-configurations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Basic configurations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="configuring-dnf"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Configuring dnf&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The next step is optional, as root, the first thing I do is configure dnf, so
that it uses the most efficient packages mirrors:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;echo &amp;#39;fastestmirror=true&amp;#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/dnf/dnf.conf&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then I disable the use of deltarpm's for future updates. If you prefer to
reduce the amount of data to be downloaded in each of the future updates, skip
this step:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;echo &amp;#39;deltarpm=false&amp;#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/dnf/dnf.conf&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always keep each of the packages from which any program is installed on my
system, including those that are downloaded as part of the updates and to
maintain the packages cache throughout the period I use a Fedora release. This
step is optional and you can skip it if you want:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;echo &amp;#39;keepcache=true&amp;#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/dnf/dnf.conf&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now I proceed to disable a service and a dnf timer. The service makes sure to
refresh the metadata cache to be able to make checks on the versions of the
packages that are in the repos and then check if there are updates available.
The timer is responsible for executing the service periodically.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I always disable both to avoid annoying bandwidth consumptions and dnf locks
while the cache is refreshed. If you have a limited bandwidth or data plan this
will help you reduce the consumption of it.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;systemctl disable dnf-makecache.service&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;systemctl disable dnf-makecache.timer&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally to make sure that the changes take effect we must restart:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;reboot&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="regenerate-the-cache-and-install-available-updates"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Regenerate the cache and install available updates&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;During the installation, you may have omitted to check the option that allows
you to install the most recent version of the mirrors packages, so your system
could be outdated even if you have used the network installation medium.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To apply the most recent updates and use the most efficient mirrors it is
necessary to regenerate the metadata cache.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Fedora maintains a cache for each user, one for the root user, another for the
normal user, in my case pionen. So we must regenerate both caches if you want
to perform tasks as administrator or simple queries that do not require
administrator privileges:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As a normal non-root user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;dnf clean all&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="go"&gt;dnf makecache&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then, as a normal non-root user, we execute the following commands, where we
pass the statement in quotes as a parameter to the root user:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf clean all&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;

&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf makecache&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We check for available updates and enter our root password:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf --refresh check-upgrade&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If there are updates available, we apply them with:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf upgrade&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If updates have been applied, it is recommended to restart the system in order
to make use of the most recent version of all the programs, for example the
kernel:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;reboot&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</content><category term="dnf"></category><category term="fc29"></category><category term="fedora"></category><category term="postinstall"></category></entry></feed>