<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<rss version="2.0"><channel><title>porfirio's blog - Porfirio Páiz</title><link>https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/</link><description></description><lastBuildDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 21:00:00 -0600</lastBuildDate><item><title>Anaconda and LVM on LUKS</title><link>https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/posts/2017/03/30/anaconda-and-lvm-on-luks.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Previously I had updated my laptop from Fedora 22 to Fedora 23 when F22 had
more than 6 months since it reached its End of Life, it is also possible reuse
partitions created for F22 so that they can be used to install the new Fedora
release and keep all the files contained in the Logical Volume that serves as
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/home&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how to achieve this without compromising the
integrity of our information or the other operating systems installed in our
Desktop/Laptop.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;As we saw in the previous post, it is possible to make an upgrade, this is great
to have the ability to do this, but the idea of downloading all packages, and
then updating them at once, is something I do not know if I want do, frankly,
doing fresh installs and setting everything to as it was before is something
I like and enjoy doing. It also represents less burden for the computer, since
it only downloads the minimum packages to have a functional system, anything
else I may need can be later installed on demand.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once all the files contained in our systems have a proper backup, we can begin
with the installation process without the fear of something going wrong, you
never know what could go wrong until it goes wrong XD.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="creating-an-installation-media"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Creating an Installation Media&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to create an installation medium, for this we must download
the Fedora 25 ISO file. Since Fedora 21 I have been using the netinstall image,
according to Chapter 2 of the &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://docs.fedoraproject.org/en-US/Fedora/25/html/Installation_Guide/chap-downloading-fedora.html"&gt;Fedora Installation Guide&lt;/a&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The netinstall image boots directly into the installation environment, and
uses the online Fedora package repositories as the installation source.
With a netinstall image, you can select a wide variety of packages to
create a customized installation of Fedora.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The Fedora Server netinstall image is a universal one, and can be used to
install any Fedora flavor or your own set of favorite packages.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="downloading-the-image-everything-netinstall"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Downloading the image Everything netinstall&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;I'd rather use the netinstall ISO image of &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://alt.fedoraproject.org/en/"&gt;Fedora Everything&lt;/a&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Apparently, the Everything netinstall image does not have a torrent seeder for
download:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://torrent.fedoraproject.org/"&gt;https://torrent.fedoraproject.org/&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;So we must use the conventional method of direct download, for this we will
make use of the command line.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download the image for 32bit systems use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;wget -N -t 0 -c https://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/fedora/linux/releases/25/Everything/i386/iso/Fedora-Everything-netinst-i386-25-1.3.iso&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To download the image for 64bit systems use the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;wget -N -t 0 -c https://download.fedoraproject.org/pub/fedora/linux/releases/25/Everything/x86_64/iso/Fedora-Everything-netinst-x86_64-25-1.3.iso&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;dl class="docutils"&gt;
&lt;dt&gt;Where:&lt;/dt&gt;
&lt;dd&gt;&lt;p class="first"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;-N&lt;/cite&gt; downloads the file with the same time and date stamp when it was first
uploaded to the servers.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;cite&gt;-t 0&lt;/cite&gt; in case the download is interrupted due to problems of connection
this will attempt to make an automatic reconnection, if we leave the time in
&lt;cite&gt;0&lt;/cite&gt; will reconnect immediately.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p class="last"&gt;&lt;cite&gt;-c&lt;/cite&gt; indicates that the download must be continued in the byte that was left
pending when the donwload was interrupted.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/dd&gt;
&lt;/dl&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This is a small contingency measure in case we do not have access to a network
stable enough.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;we can also verify the integrity of the downloaded image using the checksum
file. we only have to download the file and save it in the same directory
containing the ISO image:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;wget -N -t 0 -c https://alt.fedoraproject.org/es/static/checksums/Fedora-Everything-25-1.3-x86_64-CHECKSUM&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then we execute the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;sha256sum -c Fedora-Everything-25-1.3-x86_64-CHECKSUM&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="writing-the-iso-image-on-a-usb"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Writing the ISO image on a USB&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To burn the ISO image to an USB drive we will use the &lt;strong&gt;Fedora Media Writer&lt;/strong&gt;
tool. If you are using Windows you can install Fedora Media Writer using the
next link:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://getfedora.org/fmw/FedoraMediaWriter-win32-4.0.7.exe"&gt;https://getfedora.org/fmw/FedoraMediaWriter-win32-4.0.7.exe&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For MacOS:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;a class="reference external" href="https://getfedora.org/fmw/FedoraMediaWriter-osx-4.0.7.dmg"&gt;https://getfedora.org/fmw/FedoraMediaWriter-osx-4.0.7.dmg&lt;/a&gt;&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;If you are using Fedora 23 or higher you can install Fedora Media Writer with
following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf install mediawriter&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before running Fedora Media Writer it is advisable to disconnect any removable
storage device that may be plugged in our system, this to avoid possible
confusion. Then we connect the USB memory that we will use and until then run
Fedora Media Writer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The steps to follow are very simple, we select:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;ol class="arabic simple"&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Custom image.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Navigate to the directory where the ISO image was previously downloaded.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Select the USB.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Click &lt;cite&gt;Write to disk&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Enter your user password if you are in the &lt;cite&gt;wheel&lt;/cite&gt; group or the &lt;cite&gt;root&lt;/cite&gt;
password in case we are not in the admins group.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;li&gt;Done.&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="booting-from-usb"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Booting from USB&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case I have configured my laptop to start in &lt;cite&gt;UEFI mode&lt;/cite&gt; and with
&lt;cite&gt;Secure Boot&lt;/cite&gt; enabled.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Creating our installation media with Fedora Media Writer guarantees that the
installation medium will work in any possible scenario.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To access the Boot Manager on my laptop, I only need to press the &lt;strong&gt;Enter&lt;/strong&gt;
key while the &lt;strong&gt;Lenovo&lt;/strong&gt; logo is displayed, this is a indicator, in my case,
that the machine is booting in UEFI mode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="starting-the-fedora-25-installation-process"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Starting the Fedora 25 Installation Process&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;For this section of the post I will use screenshots and a brief description of
them.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, the Internet connection.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Installation media created from netinstall images depends exclusively on an
Internet connection, either wired via RJ45 port (Ethernet) or via Wireless
(Using our WiFi card), in my case the netinstall setup detects both network
cards. Fedora netinstall contain a set of drivers that allow us to make use of
certain network cards, in case our network card is not detected it might be due
to our device is not supported by Fedora, this is for legal reasons. Fedora only
includes FLOSS drivers or that its manufacturers make explicit mention of its
terms of use and distribution policy.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;My T440p comes equipped with an &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://ark.intel.com/products/60019/Intel-Ethernet-Connection-I217-LM"&gt;Intel® Ethernet Wired Network Card
Connection I217-LM&lt;/a&gt;
and an &lt;a class="reference external" href="http://ark.intel.com/products/75174/Intel-Wireless-N-7260"&gt;Intel® Wireless-N 7260 Wireless Network Card&lt;/a&gt;,
both cards were detected during installation, in the office I only have access
to WiFi networks so I used the Wireless card.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0000.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this first image of the installation summary, the first thing we must do
is to get connected to any of the available networks whether we use a Wired
network or WiFi network, for this we click on the &lt;cite&gt;NETWORK &amp;amp; HOST NAME&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Then selecting Wireless and activating the card; we select one Network of those
available; we change the name of our Desktop/Laptop and click &lt;cite&gt;Apply&lt;/cite&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0002.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click &lt;cite&gt;Done&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;cite&gt;LOCALIZATION&lt;/cite&gt; section I added the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;French (International (AltGr dead keys)&lt;/tt&gt;
and removed &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;English (US)&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0005.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;You can see a short test, when by pressing the &lt;cite&gt;AltGr + a&lt;/cite&gt; key and other vowels,
the result is accentuated vowels.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;cite&gt;TIME &amp;amp; DATE&lt;/cite&gt; section I always enable &lt;cite&gt;Network Time&lt;/cite&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0007.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We also select our &lt;cite&gt;Region&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;City&lt;/cite&gt;, based on this, the time and date are set.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Up to now we have configured the following sections:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0008.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Now we must configure the &lt;cite&gt;SOFTWARE&lt;/cite&gt; section, specifically &lt;cite&gt;INSTALLATION SOURCE&lt;/cite&gt;...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this section we mark &lt;cite&gt;On the Network:&lt;/cite&gt; and select &lt;cite&gt;Closest mirror&lt;/cite&gt;, we also
make sure to uncheck the &lt;cite&gt;Updates&lt;/cite&gt; option...&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0009.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This way the installer will use the online repositories to download the required
packages for the installation, using the nearest server that commonly is not the
closest geographically, but the most efficient and with better times in terms
of data transfer.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By unchecking &lt;cite&gt;Updates&lt;/cite&gt; we are telling the installer to use the latest packages
that are available in the repo.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We wait for the package group metadata to be downloaded, the section &lt;cite&gt;SOFTWARE SELECTION&lt;/cite&gt;
depends on this:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0011.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In &lt;cite&gt;SOFTWARE SELECTION&lt;/cite&gt; I chose &lt;cite&gt;Fedora Custom Operating System&lt;/cite&gt;, which
represents a very minimal package selection, with no graphical environment, only
a few packages groups as follows:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;Environment Group: Fedora Custom Operating System&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; Environment-Id: custom-environment&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; Description: Basic building block for a custom Fedora system.&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; Mandatory Groups:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;   Core&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt; Optional Groups:&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;   Guest Agents&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;span class="go"&gt;   Standard&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally we have reached the &lt;cite&gt;SYSTEM&lt;/cite&gt; section, select &lt;cite&gt;INSTALLATION DESTINATION&lt;/cite&gt;.
In &lt;cite&gt;Device Selection&lt;/cite&gt;, in &lt;cite&gt;Local Stardard Disk&lt;/cite&gt; select the hard disk that has
the Fedora installation with the existing partitions we want to reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the &lt;cite&gt;Other Storage Options&lt;/cite&gt; section, under &lt;cite&gt;Partitioning&lt;/cite&gt; we select &lt;cite&gt;I will
Configure partitioning&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The following menu is shown below, in which we will click on &lt;cite&gt;Unknown&lt;/cite&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0013.png" /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once we click &lt;cite&gt;Unknown&lt;/cite&gt; the other existing partitions will be displayed. we will
focus on the partitions &lt;strong&gt;sda2&lt;/strong&gt;, &lt;strong&gt;sda9&lt;/strong&gt; and &lt;strong&gt;sda10&lt;/strong&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0014.png" /&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sda2&lt;/strong&gt; is the ESP (EFI Partition System) partition, this partition
contains the other *.efi files; every OS that has been installed on our
computer in UEFI mode has an *.efi file that will be linked to our GRUB,
which allows us to choose which OS to boot during the first few seconds
after our computer is turned on. &lt;strong&gt;You should never mark&lt;/strong&gt; this partition to
be formatted. &lt;strong&gt;sda2&lt;/strong&gt; will be mounted on &lt;cite&gt;/boot/efi&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sda9&lt;/strong&gt; is the partition I will mount in &lt;cite&gt;/boot&lt;/cite&gt;, this partition should not
be encrypted, since inside there are files needed for the OS to be loaded,
in example the kernel. If we encrypt this partition we will not be
able  to load the kernels on boot.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;sda10&lt;/strong&gt; is the partition that was encrypted using LUKS, which contains
the &lt;cite&gt;Volume Group&lt;/cite&gt; which contains the other logical volumes that serve as
&lt;cite&gt;/&lt;/cite&gt;, &lt;cite&gt;/home&lt;/cite&gt; and &lt;cite&gt;swap&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After selecting &lt;strong&gt;sda10&lt;/strong&gt; you are prompted for the encryption password that will
grant you access to the &lt;cite&gt;Volume Group&lt;/cite&gt; containing the mentioned partitions. It
is shown as the existing Fedora 23 installation, which was originally the F22
that we updated in the previous post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0015.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We click on &lt;cite&gt;Fedora Linux 23 for x86_64&lt;/cite&gt; and we can see the logical volumes that
we will reuse.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;By clicking &lt;cite&gt;/home&lt;/cite&gt;, we make sure to assign a &lt;cite&gt;Mount Point&lt;/cite&gt; for this Logical
Volumen. We make sure that the &lt;cite&gt;Reformat&lt;/cite&gt; checkbox is &lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; checked, and click
on &lt;cite&gt;Update Settings&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0017.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the following image we can see that the logical volume &lt;cite&gt;fedora_lilit-home&lt;/cite&gt;
was reassigned to &lt;cite&gt;New Fedora 25 Installation&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0018.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We select &lt;cite&gt;/boot/efi&lt;/cite&gt;, which is nothing more than the ESP partition located in
&lt;strong&gt;sda2&lt;/strong&gt;, we make sure to assign a &lt;cite&gt;Mount Point&lt;/cite&gt; for this Logical Volume, which
in this case would be &lt;cite&gt;/boot/efi&lt;/cite&gt;. we make sure that the checkbox &lt;cite&gt;Reformat&lt;/cite&gt; is
&lt;strong&gt;not&lt;/strong&gt; checked, and click on &lt;cite&gt;Update Settings&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0019.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We select &lt;cite&gt;/&lt;/cite&gt;, this logical volume served as &lt;cite&gt;/&lt;/cite&gt; for F23, so to be able to reuse
it we must mark it to format. we assign &lt;cite&gt;/&lt;/cite&gt; as the point, I assign a file system
ext4, we ensure that the checkbox &lt;cite&gt;Reformat&lt;/cite&gt; &lt;strong&gt;is&lt;/strong&gt; marked, and click on
&lt;cite&gt;Update Settings&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0023.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Select &lt;cite&gt;swap&lt;/cite&gt;, mark the checkbox and click &lt;cite&gt;Update Settings&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0025.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We select &lt;cite&gt;/boot&lt;/cite&gt;, here is where the F23 kernels were stored, so to reuse this
partition it is required to format it. we assign a &lt;cite&gt;Mount Point&lt;/cite&gt; &lt;cite&gt;/boot&lt;/cite&gt;, then
click &lt;cite&gt;Reformat&lt;/cite&gt;, in my case I assign an ext4 file system and click &lt;cite&gt;Update Settings&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0030.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Click on &lt;cite&gt;Done&lt;/cite&gt; and accept the changes that will be made.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To finish just click on &lt;cite&gt;Begin Installation&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0032.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;We assign a user password and ROOT password. And wait, now we must wait for the
download of the packages and their installation to finish:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0037.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After done, click &lt;cite&gt;Reboot&lt;/cite&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/anaconda-screenshots/0053.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In my case I had to do a series of steps after the installation that the
we will see in the next post.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Porfirio Páiz</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 30 Mar 2017 21:00:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:porfiriopaiz.github.io,2017-03-30:/site/posts/2017/03/30/anaconda-and-lvm-on-luks.html</guid><category>anaconda</category><category>fc25</category><category>fedora</category><category>luks</category><category>lvm</category></item><item><title>Upgrading from Fedora 22 to Fedora 23</title><link>https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/posts/2017/03/26/upgrading-from-fedora-22-to-fedora-23.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;From May 26th in 2015 to November 22th in 2016 I was using Fedora 22 on my
Lenovo ThinkPad T440p, which is equivalent to a year and a half running F22. On
July 19th of 2016 F22 entered &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/End_of_life"&gt;EOL&lt;/a&gt;
status, which means that you will not receive any further security or
maintenance updates, so upgrading to a newer stable version was recommended.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will explain how to update to Fedora 23 using the dnf package
manager.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;After using Fedora 22 for a year and a half, the packages cache had taken
approximately 10GB of space on my hard drive:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/fc22_to_fc23/screenshot_from_2016-11-22_16-05-06.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To tell dnf to preserve the packages downloaded in the cache it is required to
add the following line to the dnf configuration file &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/etc/dnf/dnf.conf&lt;/tt&gt;:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;quot;echo &amp;#39;keepcache = true&amp;#39; &amp;gt;&amp;gt; /etc/dnf/dnf.conf&amp;quot;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="upgrading-fedora-23"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Upgrading Fedora 23&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="prerequisites-for-upgrading"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Prerequisites for upgrading&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First, we make sure we have enough space on our &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/&lt;/tt&gt; partition, since during
the update process we will need to download the most recent version of each and
every single of the packages installed in our system. Whereas there is a
possibility that our cache may be full, it is good to remove the packages stored
in it to freed space in case we need:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf clean all&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Before we continue, we need to make sure that our system has installed the
latest updates available from the different repositories enabled in our system.
To do this, we must reconstruct the packages metadata cache and then apply the
recent upgrades:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf makecache&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/fc22_to_fc23/screenshot_from_2016-11-22_17-23-27.png" /&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf upgrade&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="install-the-dnf-plugin-system-upgrade-plugin"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Install the dnf-plugin-system-upgrade plugin&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;&lt;strong&gt;DNF System Upgrade&lt;/strong&gt; can upgrade your system to a more recent version of
Fedora, using a mechanism similar to that used for offline package updates.
Packages are donwloaded while the system is running normally, and then the
system is restarted in a special environment (implemented as a systmend
target) to install them. Once the installation of the packages is complete,
the system reboots but this time in the new Fedora version.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;The first step is to install the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;dnf-plugin-system-upgrade&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; plugin:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf install dnf-plugin-system-upgrade&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And now let's proceed to download the packages needed to upgrade to Fedora 23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This process will download each and every one of the packages that we have
installed in our system, in its most recent version available for the release
that we indicate, in this case the release will be &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;23&lt;/tt&gt;.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf system-upgrade download --refresh --best --allowerasing --releasever=23&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the next screenshot you can see the number of packages to download and the
amount of data that implies downloading them:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;img alt="" class="align-center" src="https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/images/fc22_to_fc23/screenshot_from_2016-11-22_17-34-42.png" /&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In the same way it is possible to upgrade to Fedora 24, although I do not
recommend jumping to a &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;(n + 2)&lt;/tt&gt; Fedora version, that is, moving from Fedora
22 to Fedora 24. At the moment, the most recent stable versions are Fedora 24
and Fedora 25; Fedora 26 is &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Releases/Branched"&gt;Branched&lt;/a&gt;
and &lt;a class="reference external" href="https://fedoraproject.org/wiki/Releases/Rawhide"&gt;Rawhide&lt;/a&gt; the version in
continuous development. To upgrade to any of the above versions, only the
&lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;number&lt;/tt&gt; parameter should be edited in the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;--releasever=number&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; option, 24
for F24, 25 for F25, 26 for Fedora Branched and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;rawhide&lt;/tt&gt; to upgrade to
Rawhide. It should be noted that both Branched and Rawhide are not stable
versions of Fedora, so its use is only recommended for more experienced users.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrading to Fedora 24:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf system-upgrade download --refresh --best --allowerasing --releasever=24&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrading to Fedora 25:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf system-upgrade download --refresh --best --allowerasing --releasever=25&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Upgrading to Fedora Rawhide:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf system-upgrade download --refresh --best --allowerasing --releasever=rawhide&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, once it downloads the packages, it is necessary to restart the system by
executing the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf system-upgrade reboot&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;This will restart the system. Then the system should boot again using the same
(newer) kernel, but this time it will start the upgrade process from Fedora 22
to Fedora 23.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Porfirio Páiz</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 26 Mar 2017 16:46:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:porfiriopaiz.github.io,2017-03-26:/site/posts/2017/03/26/upgrading-from-fedora-22-to-fedora-23.html</guid><category>dnf</category><category>eol</category><category>fc22</category><category>fc23</category><category>fedora</category><category>system-upgrade</category></item><item><title>IRC with irssi</title><link>https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/posts/2016/11/03/irc-with-irssi.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;From my beginnings in the Free Software and GNU/Linux, one of the features
that caught my attention is the power of the command line in this operating
system. From moving between different directories or installing an operating
system completely from scratch, these are some of the routine tasks you can
achive from the terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;!-- TEASER_END --&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In this post I will show how to configure irssi to automate some of the steps to
carry out in order to access a chat room, as it is connecting to the server,
authenticate and then joining the differents channels that are of interest.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="installing-irssi"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Installing irssi&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To install irssi in fedora, just open a terminal and type the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;dnf install irssi&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And to install irssi in debian:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;su -c &amp;#39;apt-get install irssi&amp;#39;&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="running-irssi"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Running irssi&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;To run irssi, open a terminal and type the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;irssi&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="configurations"&gt;
&lt;h2&gt;Configurations&lt;/h2&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="server-configurations"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Server Configurations&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;All these commands must be executed on a irssi session.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;First we will remove the existing server configuration that we want to automate.
With &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;/server list&lt;/tt&gt; we can view existing servers:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;/server list&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In our case we will remove the existing configuration of Freenode.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;/server remove chat.freenode.net&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;And add the new configuration with the following command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;/SERVER ADD -auto -network Freenode chat.freenode.net 6667 your_nick_password&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In which &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-auto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; defines the connection to the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Freenode&lt;/tt&gt; server as
automatic and &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;your_nick_password&lt;/tt&gt; is your user password.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;div class="section" id="adding-channels"&gt;
&lt;h3&gt;Adding Channels&lt;/h3&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Similarly, it is possible to add channels to this server in order to get
connected automatically on each login, for this run the following command in our
irssi session:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;/channel add -auto #fedora Freenode&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;In which &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;&lt;span class="pre"&gt;-auto&lt;/span&gt;&lt;/tt&gt; allows us joining to &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;#fedora&lt;/tt&gt; channel at &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;Freenode&lt;/tt&gt;
server automatically at each login.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Finally, every time we make a change in our configuration, we must save changes
with the command:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;/save&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;irssi takes the user name of your current session on the system as the user for
your session in irc, to prevent this from happening if the name of your session
in the system does not match your user at Freenode, you should run irssi with
the following parameter:&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;div class="highlight"&gt;&lt;pre&gt;&lt;span&gt;&lt;/span&gt;&lt;span class="go"&gt;irssi -n nick&lt;/span&gt;
&lt;/pre&gt;&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Where &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;nick&lt;/tt&gt; is your user nick on Freenode IRC.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;p&gt;Once you've added all your channels of interest from the Freenode server and
saved the changes, you only need to run in a terminal the &lt;tt class="docutils literal"&gt;irssi&lt;/tt&gt; command and
automatically you will be connected to the server and all the channels you've
added without needing to authenticate manually and without risking anyone from
reading your password while you type it. All this from a terminal.&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
&lt;/div&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Porfirio Páiz</dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 03 Nov 2016 21:20:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:porfiriopaiz.github.io,2016-11-03:/site/posts/2016/11/03/irc-with-irssi.html</guid><category>cli</category><category>irc</category></item><item><title>Hello World!</title><link>https://porfiriopaiz.github.io/site/posts/2016/10/09/hello-world.html</link><description>&lt;p&gt;Hello World from Pelican!&lt;/p&gt;
</description><dc:creator xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/">Porfirio Páiz</dc:creator><pubDate>Sun, 09 Oct 2016 20:49:00 -0600</pubDate><guid isPermaLink="false">tag:porfiriopaiz.github.io,2016-10-09:/site/posts/2016/10/09/hello-world.html</guid></item></channel></rss>